<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Categories on Adam Drake</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/categories.html</link><description>Recent content in Categories from Adam Drake</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://adamdrake.com/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Unreasonably Deep Dive Into Project Euler Problem 4</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-4.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-4.html</guid><description>Or: How to make your solution 8000x faster with math and short-circuit evaluation. Introduction It has been a couple of years since my last Project Eueler effort, An Unreasonably Deep Dive into Project Euler Problem 3, and since I&amp;rsquo;ve also been wanting to do more work with Rust recently, I thought it would be a good opportunity to do both things at once by doing Project Euler problem 4 in Rust instead of my default of Go as before.</description></item><item><title>Posts</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/posts.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/posts.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Digital Maneuver</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/digital-maneuver.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/digital-maneuver.html</guid><description>BLUF: A Newsletter Digital Maneuver is the ability to quickly build or modify software applications or systems in order to gain a decisive advantage over a competitor. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent decades helping organizations increase their digital maneuverability and have recently created the Digital Maneuver newsletter in order to distribute some of these ideas and other curated content to people who are interested in achieving that in their teams. If you want to learn more ways to deliver software faster in your organization, sign up here.</description></item><item><title>Developing your AI BS detector (v2)</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/developing-your-ai-bs-detector-v2.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/developing-your-ai-bs-detector-v2.html</guid><description>Introduction In April 2018 I gave a lecture at an event in Toronto which I titled Developing Your AI BS Detector.. That event was designed to be a discussion around &amp;ldquo;Rational AI in the Enterprise&amp;rdquo; and I&amp;rsquo;ve found that since then others have been interested in hosting a version of the lecture as well.
Recently, I updated the slides a bit and changed the focus of the lecture somewhat to make it more clear and accessible.</description></item><item><title>Technical is tactical</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/technical-is-tactical.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/technical-is-tactical.html</guid><description>Intro: levels of war The US Department of the Army publishes a Field Manual called Operations (FM 3-0 (PDF)), a doctrinal guide for conducting military operations. In it, three levels of war are described. They are:
The strategic level (such as national policy) The operational level (such as campaigns and major operations) The tactical level (including battles and small-unit actions) At the strategic level, national interests and policy inform national and multinational military objectives, and global plans for achieving those objectives are developed.</description></item><item><title>Novel Results Considered Harmful</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/novel-results-considered-harmful.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/novel-results-considered-harmful.html</guid><description>Introduction Ravi Adve from University of Toronto graciously invited me to give a public lecture at the university earlier this summer. I was very grateful for the opportunity.
The university&amp;rsquo;s facilities were fantastic, and Ravi did a wonderful job organizing everything. The audience was engaging and asked thoughtful questions, and the attendance was much higher than I had anticipated for a Tuesday morning lecture in the middle of summer! There was great representation from multiple departments, including Electrical and Computer Engineering, Computer Science, and Mathematics.</description></item><item><title>Always Be Shipping</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/always-be-shipping.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/always-be-shipping.html</guid><description>Introduction Sometimes when I&amp;rsquo;m advising startups the topic of a feature freeze comes up in a variety of contexts. The context I&amp;rsquo;m referring to is one in which technical debt, poor architecture decisions, and other related issues, have accumulated in a system to the point that it has become seemingly unmanageable. The situation has allegedly become so dire that all new development of features for the business must stop in order to dedicate all developer time and energy to cleaning up the mess.</description></item><item><title>Leaders Eat Last</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/leaders-eat-last.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/leaders-eat-last.html</guid><description>Introduction When leading teams, one of the most important things to keep in mind is to lead from a perspective of wanting the team to grow and improve in order to achieve a higher goal. The biggest part of that is taking care of the people on the team. This can mean things people may typically think of, like supporting and encouraging someone on your team while they pursue their career goals.</description></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence and The Heilmeier Catechism</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/artificial-intelligence-and-the-heilmeier-catechism.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/artificial-intelligence-and-the-heilmeier-catechism.html</guid><description>As part of my advising work, I encounter a plethora of companies. Most of these companies want to begin, improve, or continue initiatives surrounding Artificial Intelligence (AI), Machine Learning, Data Science, Data Analytics, or other such labels applied to a project wherein data is used to accomplish some business objectives.
The difficulty is that these labels often serve to obfuscate the true nature of the project in order to make it sound more exciting, and to entice funding from those with the power to grant it.</description></item><item><title>Speak with Confidence</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/speak-with-confidence.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/speak-with-confidence.html</guid><description>Introduction When I&amp;rsquo;m asked to spend some time with a startup to help them continue their growth trajectory, by far the most common issues I help to solve are problems relating to leadership. Specifically, I&amp;rsquo;m usually asked by the investors and/or executive team to work very closely with the technology leadership in order to help them improve their output. The best way to improve output is to improve leadership skills.</description></item><item><title>Don't Categorize, Prioritize!</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/dont-categorize-prioritize.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/dont-categorize-prioritize.html</guid><description>Introduction When I begin an advising engagement with a client, one of the first things I try to understand is what their top priorities are as an organization. This seems like an obvious step, but there is a subtle difference between what most people say are priorities, and what they actually do when they think they&amp;rsquo;re setting priorities. This is because people say they prioritize, but they actually categorize.</description></item><item><title>Three Things Your People Need To Know</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/three-things-your-people-need-to-know.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/three-things-your-people-need-to-know.html</guid><description>Introduction As part of my work with scale-up companies, a critical component of the process I follow during an on-site visit is having interviews and discussions with a variety of people. I have these discussions with everyone at the company, not just the CEO and CTO with whom I most often closely work. People who are lower on the organizational chart often know more than the executive team about what is actually going on in the company.</description></item><item><title>Scalable Machine Learning with Fully Anonymized Data</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/scalable-machine-learning-with-fully-anonymized-data.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/scalable-machine-learning-with-fully-anonymized-data.html</guid><description>Note: This article will likely be revised and expanded before being submitted for review and publication. At the moment it is missing critical sections, that will be added later. If we have suggestions for improvement, please send them to me directly.
Abstract In this article I will discuss the well-known technique of feature hashing, but with the modification of performing the hashing step on the client-side before sending data to a server or daemon performing model training and prediction.</description></item><item><title>Big Data, Small Machine</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/big-data-small-machine.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/big-data-small-machine.html</guid><description>Introduction I was honored to be invited by DevTO to give a talk at their May meetup. The organizers were keen to have someone speak about high-performance machine learning, and I was happy to oblige.
The general thesis of the talk is that, for the purposes of machine learning, setting up large compute clusters is wholly unnecessary. Furthermore, it should generally be considered harmful as those efforts are extremely time consuming and detract from solving the actual machine learning problem at hand.</description></item><item><title>Hello, Recruiter!</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/hello-recruiter.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/hello-recruiter.html</guid><description>Hello Recruiter!
Thank you very much for your message and your consideration.
In order for me to consider the role more fully and determine if a call is warranted, would you please provide more information? Please send over a JD/role description including the following:
The specific company that is hiring How they see the role and its associated responsibilities fitting into the future of the company Composition, size, and working style of the current team Reporting line for the role (up to Board/investors and two levels down) Compensation details, including a breakdown between fixed/variable cash and options/equity/bonus, if any Any additional information that you think would be relevant in considering if the role is a good fit I&amp;rsquo;m happy to consider the above information and determine if the role is a good fit for me.</description></item><item><title>Developing Your AI BS Detector</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/developing-your-ai-bs-detector.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/developing-your-ai-bs-detector.html</guid><description>Introduction I gave a talk at MaRS on this topic. The event was put on by Steve O&amp;rsquo;Neil and his team, who all did an excellent job. The venue was packed to standing-room only with a fantastic audience of 300-400 people.
The goal of the event was to have a discussion around &amp;ldquo;Rational AI in the Enterprise.&amp;rdquo; I think all of the speakers did a wonderful job of honoring the topic.</description></item><item><title>Serverless with Lambda, API Gateway, and Go</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/serverless-with-lambda-api-gateway-and-go.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/serverless-with-lambda-api-gateway-and-go.html</guid><description>Intro Some time ago I made TinySite and I wrote an article about building the Biggest Smallest Website. As part of that work, I also built CompressTest in order to provide some insight on size of data post-compression for a few of the compress methods in the Go standard library.
Those services were running on EC2 instances via Elastic Beanstalk, and while the cost wasn&amp;rsquo;t great, I have other side projects which, like those, require few resources and therefore result in EC2 instances which are mostly idling.</description></item><item><title>Writing the job description</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/writing-the-job-description.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/writing-the-job-description.html</guid><description>Writing the job description Ahh, the job description. It is the face of your company on job search sites. It sets the tone for all the rest of the hiring process that follows. It has the power to make or break your hiring success. It&amp;rsquo;s a shame they&amp;rsquo;re so often badly written.
A good job description isn&amp;rsquo;t so different from a bad one. Mostly, it just has some of the letters in different places.</description></item><item><title>The biggest smallest website</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/the-biggest-smallest-website.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/the-biggest-smallest-website.html</guid><description>Introduction I was surfing the web and, as is often the case, I stumbled upon a cool project: the FastestWebsiteEver. It&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;the greatest website to ever fit in a single TCP packet.&amp;rdquo;
I had a think about that for a minute, and checked out the actual site, and noticed that it&amp;rsquo;s approximately 1130 bytes transferred. Now depending on how fresh you are on your OSI Model, you might remember that there are 7 layers.</description></item><item><title>From Enterprise Decentralization, to Tokenization, and Beyond!</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/from-enterprise-decentralization-to-tokenization-and-beyond.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/from-enterprise-decentralization-to-tokenization-and-beyond.html</guid><description>Note: This is post which I co-authord with Don Gossman and is cross-posted to the Ocean Protocol site.
We are putting together a blog series that tackles the lowly subject of enterprise transformation. Of particular importance will be data decentralization and how it will drastically change the way in which we interact and leverage data assets in the not-too-distant future (teaser: see Ocean Protocol). Simple topic, we know.
In this first post, we will focus on the pitfalls of centralizing and consolidating IT capabilities, and what alternatives exist.</description></item><item><title>Filtering for better tech hiring</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/filtering-for-better-tech-hiring.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/filtering-for-better-tech-hiring.html</guid><description>Filtering for better tech In a previous article, we discussed a redesigned hiring process based on generating inbound demand coupled with effective automated filters. Ensuring that this process is streamlined requires further filters that determine the quality of your candidates with minimum friction at each step from application to employment. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll talk a bit more about the steps in that filtering process, how to design them, and what to consider along the way.</description></item><item><title>Rethinking hiring</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/rethinking-hiring.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/rethinking-hiring.html</guid><description>Rethink hiring: how automation helps tech startups get ahead Hiring is almost always difficult, especially when the hiring process isn&amp;rsquo;t designed in a way that supports the company&amp;rsquo;s objectives. In this article I&amp;rsquo;ll outline a few key points to imagining and redesigning the hiring process. We&amp;rsquo;ll discuss a focus on generating inbound applicant flow, minimizing steps in the hiring process by maximizing information gained at each step, and increasing use of automation throughout.</description></item><item><title>Teammate to Team Lead</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/teammate-to-team-lead.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/teammate-to-team-lead.html</guid><description>Introduction Growing organizations go through many changes on the journey of scaling up. A common one is the creation of new teams, and consequently, new team leaders. As startups move from teams of people, to teams of teams, former peers become leaders and must learn to excel in their new role. How do you tackle the challenges of being viewed differently and commanding a new level of respect, while at the same time remaining humble and approachable to your team?</description></item><item><title>Faster command line tools with Go</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/faster-command-line-tools-with-go.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/faster-command-line-tools-with-go.html</guid><description>Update After some input from u/epiris on Reddit, I improved the code a bit further by changing the way bytestreams are scanned. Current fastest runtime is 0.308s for 10,512,769 rows, or about 34 Million rows per second. Since the file is 184 Megabytes, this is a processing speed of about 600 Megabytes per second, which is probably close to the read speed limit of my SSD.
It all started with a blog post, Faster Command Line Tools in D.</description></item><item><title>Enough with the microservices</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/enough-with-the-microservices.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/enough-with-the-microservices.html</guid><description>Tl;dr: Don’t even consider microservices unless you have a system that’s too complex to manage as a monolith. The majority of software systems should be built as a single monolithic application. Do pay attention to good modularity within that monolith, but don’t try to separate it into separate services.
&amp;ndash; Martin Fowler
If you can’t build a well-structured monolith, what makes you think microservices is the answer?</description></item><item><title>Enough with the microservices (Chinese translation)</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/enough-with-the-microservices-chinese-translation.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/enough-with-the-microservices-chinese-translation.html</guid><description>&lt;p>资深架构师Adam Drake在他的博客上分享了他对微服务的看法，他从自己的经验出发，结合Martin Fowler对微服务的见解，帮助想要采用微服务的公司重新审视微服务。以下内容已获得作者翻译授权，查看英文原文 &lt;a href="https://adamdrake.com/enough-with-the-microservices.html">Enough with the microservices。&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>简介&lt;/p>
&lt;p>关于微服务的优势和劣势已经有过太多的讨论，不过我仍然看到很多成长型初创公司对它进行着盲目崇拜。冒着“重复发明轮子”的风险（Martin Fowler已经写过“Microservice Premium”的文章），我想把我的一些想法写下来，在必要的时候可以发给客户，也希望能够帮助人们避免犯下我之前见过的那些错误。在进行架构或技术选型时，将网络上找到的一些所谓的最佳实践文章作为指南，一旦做出了错误的决定，就要付出惨重的代价。如果能够帮助哪怕一个公司避免犯下这种错误，那么写这篇文章都是值得的。&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Redis Performance Triage Handbook</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/redis-performance-triage-handbook.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/redis-performance-triage-handbook.html</guid><description>Intro I do a lot of work with growth-stage startups, and many of them use Redis for all sorts of things. Sometimes as a key/value store for caching, sometimes as a message queue, sometimes as a pub/sub message broker, etc. Redis is a great tool, with great performance, when used properly. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve often seen cases where it is not used with good performance in mind, often to the detriment of system uptime and customer satisfaction.</description></item><item><title>An Unreasonably Deep Dive into Project Euler Problem 3</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-3.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-3.html</guid><description>Intro I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy as usual for the last couple of months, and haven&amp;rsquo;t really had time to extend the Project Euler series after Problem 1 and Problem 2 articles.
However, I finally did set aside some time to play around with Problem 3: finding the largest prime factor of a number.
Problem Statement The prime factors of 13195 are 5, 7, 13 and 29.
What is the largest prime factor of the number 600851475143?</description></item><item><title>The Ten-Minute Reorg</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/the-ten-minute-reorg.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/the-ten-minute-reorg.html</guid><description>I spend a lot of time working with growth-stage startups. I often see similar problems across companies when it comes to scaling up their tech teams. At a certain point, the intuitive way to grow a team breaks down, and a reorganization (&amp;ldquo;reorg&amp;rdquo;) is necessary in order to adopt a scalable structure. Where some companies may take months to design and execute a reorg, I prefer to handle the majority of it in about ten minutes.</description></item><item><title>Command and Control</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/command-and-control.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/command-and-control.html</guid><description>Introduction When I advise organizations, they often ask if I have written down or somehow codified my perspectives on leadership and operations. Until now, the answer has been a polite not yet. I simply didn&amp;rsquo;t believe I have accumulated sufficient experience to warrant writing something from a position of authority on the topic of leadership and operations in organizations. After much consideration and gentle prodding from advisory clients, I have come to understand that my perspective may be flawed.</description></item><item><title>I am Here to Win</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/i-am-here-to-win.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/i-am-here-to-win.html</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m not here to be right, I&amp;rsquo;m here to win. That&amp;rsquo;s a phrase I often keep in mind, especially when I feel my own ego getting the best of me or when I see someone else&amp;rsquo;s ego affecting their judgment. In this context, win means making progress towards a larger strategic goal, likely by achieving some intermediate objective. So if you are playing to win and not just to be right then you are putting aside your own ego and emotional involvement in order to make progress towards a larger goal.</description></item><item><title>On Confidence</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-confidence.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-confidence.html</guid><description>Bearing, presence, gravitas, and authority are all some words used to describe those who project confidence. When I am advising executives and leaders to help them with their teams, one of the topics of concern for them is confidence and how to gain it. Or at the very least, how to project confidence even when it&amp;rsquo;s not there. The latter seems to be especially concerning to those who are relatively new in their leadership positions.</description></item><item><title>On Forecasts</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-forecasts.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-forecasts.html</guid><description>Overview I was meeting with a client recently, and since it was the end of the year and they were in their budgeting process we were discussing forecasting methodologies. They were asking about their marketing function specifically, but the conversation applied more or less to all areas of the business which set targets and/or develop a budget. So basically, the whole business.
It&amp;rsquo;s important to note that in many companies budgeting and forecasting are the same thing, so this is as much a budgeting topic as a forecasting one.</description></item><item><title>Leadership and Communication</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/leadership-and-communication.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/leadership-and-communication.html</guid><description>Good leadership is hard to quantify, especially when considering intrinsic qualities like humility (which I argue is the most important quality of all). However, there are external skills which can separate effective and ineffective leaders, and communication is arguably the most fundamental of those externally-visible skills.
When a company is small, and everyone fits in a single room, then a shared vision can almost be maintained by osmosis. Additionally, at this stage a company is usually extremely focused on a narrow goal or set of goals, so there is clarity not only due to small company sizes having more efficient communication, but also because the set of objectives is small as well.</description></item><item><title>An Unreasonably Deep Dive into Project Euler Problem 2</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-2.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-2.html</guid><description>First, the problem definition:
Each new term in the Fibonacci sequence is generated by adding the previous two terms. By starting with 1 and 2, the first 10 terms will be:
1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, 34, 55, 89, &amp;hellip;
By considering the terms in the Fibonacci sequence whose values do not exceed four million, find the sum of the even-valued terms.
Classic Fibonacci problem, with a slight twist due to the summation on top.</description></item><item><title>An Unreasonably Deep Dive into Project Euler Problem 1</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-1.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/an-unreasonably-deep-dive-into-project-euler-problem-1.html</guid><description>Introduction As part of my work in keeping my technical skills sharp, I periodically go back to basics or solve old problems again in order to ensure my foundations are strong. So it was with great fun that I decided to start back at the beginning with Project Euler.
One of the techniques I also use for this sort of thing is not just to solve the problem, but to really explore it.</description></item><item><title>Remembering The Fallen</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/remembering-the-fallen.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/remembering-the-fallen.html</guid><description>Those that know me are aware that I have always had great respect for people who have served or are serving in the military. I thought it would be a nice project to create a Twitter bot that would tweet, on a given day, all the US Servicemembers killed in action on that day in prior years. You can view it on Twitter or follow @thedailyfallen directly.
I&amp;rsquo;ve had questions before about simple Data Science, Machine Learning, and software development projects before, so here is a good example of just such a project.</description></item><item><title>Competitors are Not the Problem</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/competitors-are-not-the-problem.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/competitors-are-not-the-problem.html</guid><description>I advise many successful companies, and some of them have grown very quickly to their current size and state. They developed a product or service, matched it with a market, and are experiencing a great deal of success. During the earlier parts of this journey they were acutely aware of the possibility of competitors being able to overtake them or the reality that other competitors really were jockeying for position in the market.</description></item><item><title>How Do You Punish People?</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/how-do-you-punish-people.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/how-do-you-punish-people.html</guid><description>Introduction The title of this post is literally the first question I received from someone when I was doing leadership advising at a very successful company. The company was dominant in their market and were continuing to grow internationally. The person who asked me the question was intelligent and had previously worked for a large technology organization before taking on their current role leading a department. The person knew I was there to help the executive team become more effective leaders and thereby help the company continue their along their growth trajectory, but for this person leadership was seemingly a matter of delegation and punishment.</description></item><item><title>Culture Red Flags: Who is *They*?</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/culture-red-flags-who-is-they.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/culture-red-flags-who-is-they.html</guid><description>Over the years I&amp;rsquo;ve advised many companies on how to improve their leadership capabilities in order to cultivate a more effective corporate culture and thereby achieve growth. One thing which is absolutely necessary for a company to thrive is for the culture to support collaboration and a sense of shared purpose. You need unit cohesion. You need the shared feeling that we are all one group, with one purpose, currently making progress towards one goal which supports that purpose.</description></item><item><title>What is Your Current Salary?</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/what-is-your-current-salary.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/what-is-your-current-salary.html</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve probably hired hundreds of people in my career and I also do a fair bit of mentoring for new technology professionals, especially new Data Scientists and Data Engineers, Software engineers, and similar roles. One thing that often comes up is looking for new jobs and how to go about that process. For more junior candidates especially, you are at risk of getting asked a very dangerous question; What is your current salary?</description></item><item><title>A Hackish System Command Service in Go</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/a-hackish-system-command-service-in-go.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/a-hackish-system-command-service-in-go.html</guid><description>When building data products, often the end result is either a recurring report or an API which allows for an interface with other services. In these cases, the product might be run by a cron job, or even manually, depending on the situation. When the product is part of (more frequently, at the end of) a larger data processing pipeline, this can become inefficient or problematic since steps earlier in the pipeline can cause the product to supply incorrect information or fail altogether.</description></item><item><title>Are your Functions Total?</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/are-your-functions-total.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/are-your-functions-total.html</guid><description>In recent years, and for a variety of reasons, functional programming has become an increasingly popular topic. Languages like Haskell, Scala, Clojure, and others, have had huge gains in popularity and consequently there have been many large-scale projects written in some of these languages. There has also been increasing pressure to move programming more towards the rigor of mathematics, something which I strongly support.
One thing which could get more attention in the context of functional programming is the concept of Total Functional Programming, which uses the concepts of total functions combined with specific types of recursion in order to guarantee that all your programs terminate.</description></item><item><title>Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/hooked-how-to-build-habit-forming-products.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/hooked-how-to-build-habit-forming-products.html</guid><description>I recently finished a book called Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products by Nir Eyal. The book overall expresses a nice framework for considering products and services, whether or not they should be habit-forming in the first place, and if so how to go about making that happen. The framework is very useful in that it allows for organizations to have a common language they can use to speak about their product and how they should modify or improve it.</description></item><item><title>A Quick Overview on the Kaggle Competition for Avito</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/a-quick-overview-on-the-kaggle-competition-for-avito.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/a-quick-overview-on-the-kaggle-competition-for-avito.html</guid><description>Introduction I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time for this competition, so didn&amp;rsquo;t invest much into feature engineering, creating ensembles or other things. As I participated in the Avazu competition as well, which included the use of tinrtgu&amp;rsquo;s now-famous code, I decided to use the same approach here.
Background The overall goal of the competition is to analyze user behavior in order to generate a model for recommending ads to be shown in front of users, with the success metric being whether or not the user clicks on the ad.</description></item><item><title>Transitioning to a Data-Driven Organization</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/transitioning-to-a-data-driven-organization.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/transitioning-to-a-data-driven-organization.html</guid><description>Introduction I gave a talk at the CDO Summit in Singapore on 18 June and thought it may be worthwhile to address some of the points and provide additional detail on the slides I used.
Sections below are listed by slide content and provide extra explanation.
Kardashev Scale This is simply applying the Kardashev Scale of technological advancement to the advancement of data usage in organizations. For more detail see the article I wrote on the Kardashev Scale of Data Maturity.</description></item><item><title>Makespan Minimization for Unrelated Parallel Machines with Maintenance Windows</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/makespan-minimization-for-unrelated-parallel-machines-with-maintenance-windows.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/makespan-minimization-for-unrelated-parallel-machines-with-maintenance-windows.html</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s a bit late, but last year during the Christmas break, Kaggle had a very interesting competition for the season. The story was that the toy list at Santa&amp;rsquo;s workshop was long, and elves had to make all the toys, with some constraints on their productivity rating and rest intervals. This is an adaptation of the classic problem of minimizing makespan, though with additional constraints. A good leaderboard position could be achieved using offline methods since the entire list of toys was supplied in advance, but as usual I pursued online solutions for fun and speed.</description></item><item><title>On Two-Sided Markets</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-two-sided-markets.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-two-sided-markets.html</guid><description>Many technology companies can be viewed in the context of a two-sided marketplace (TSM), a special case of a multi-sided marketplace (MSM). This view has interesting implications for the dynamics of the business in addition to how product strategy and prioritization is decided. Having worked for over 15 years in TSM environments from Online Travel, to Affiliate Marketing at Zanox, mobile ad network madvertise, and many years in Financial Services, I thought it might be useful to provide a conceptual overview of the markets, dynamics, and implications.</description></item><item><title>Moving from Type 2 to Type 3 Data Organizations</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/moving-from-type-2-to-type-3-data-organizations.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/moving-from-type-2-to-type-3-data-organizations.html</guid><description>Introduction In the previous post on the Kardashev scale for data organizations we discussed the three general types and their characteristics, but didn&amp;rsquo;t dive deeply into how to make the move from Type 2 to Type 3 (the move from Type 1 to Type 2 doesn&amp;rsquo;t really require much explanation).
The move from Type 2 to Type 3 requires more focus on data and how it integrates into the product (including developing totally new products) and a departure from focusing on the data organization as a service unit.</description></item><item><title>On Schemas</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-schemas.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-schemas.html</guid><description>Introduction Over the last few years, some people have come to see schemas of any type as a legacy hinderance which should generally be ignored, and much of the NoSQL fervor that gained momentum around 2010 was related to this. The promise was that not having schemas would set you free and that you would become more productive, agile, your application would be faster, and all kinds of other things.</description></item><item><title>The Kardashev Scale of Data Maturity</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/the-kardashev-scale-of-data-maturity.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/the-kardashev-scale-of-data-maturity.html</guid><description>Introduction For those who have read or seen much science fiction, you have probably encountered the Kardashev Scale at some point. This is a general grouping of how advanced a civilization is based on the ways it utilizes energy. At the risk of reiterating what&amp;rsquo;s already on Wikipedia:
The Kardashev scale is a method of measuring a civilization&amp;rsquo;s level of technological advancement, based on the amount of energy a civilization is able to utilize.</description></item><item><title>The Goal and the Theory of Constraints</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/the-goal-and-the-theory-of-constraints.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/the-goal-and-the-theory-of-constraints.html</guid><description>Introduction I was recently having a conversation about metrics and KPIs in a company, with the aim of finding out the things important to the company and ultimately designing an objective function for the business. This objective function is then used to determine which factors are important for the success of the business and therefore can result in the design of a closed-loop control system that can serve as a way to run and optimize the business.</description></item><item><title>Stop Collecting So Much Data</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/stop-collecting-so-much-data.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/stop-collecting-so-much-data.html</guid><description>In many discussions with people in the industry, the topic of how much data is collected or processed often arises. Although it&amp;rsquo;s useful for getting a feeling for the scale of data challenges at a company, as a metric for the skills or effectiveness of a data organization it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty useless topic. However, even when the topic is raised in the context of getting a feel for data challenges at a company, that only makes sense if all the data are necessary for solving problems.</description></item><item><title>On Data Governance</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-data-governance.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-data-governance.html</guid><description>Overview The short version, is that Data Governance is all of the business concerns surrounding data. This means things like data quality, management, risks, and similar non-technical things. It&amp;rsquo;s comprised of the kind of concerns that business people would typically have surrounding data, although the quality topic is critically important for machine learning practitioners. For our purposes, I&amp;rsquo;ll group the concerns generally into quality, management, and risks. Each of those things can be pursued very deeply, but we need only an overview in order to make some key points.</description></item><item><title>On Salary Negotiations</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-salary-negotiations.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-salary-negotiations.html</guid><description>Salary negotiations are often presented from the perspective of a potential employee, but I rarely read anything regarding strategies for companies who want to do their best to hire a particular candidate. As someone not formally trained in HR, my opinions on the topic have been developed strictly through my experiences. If you&amp;rsquo;re an HR expert and think I&amp;rsquo;m crazy then I ask you contact me and help me improve my perspective.</description></item><item><title>Using Twitter as a Stream Processing Source</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/using-twitter-as-a-stream-processing-source.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/using-twitter-as-a-stream-processing-source.html</guid><description>Recently, I was providing a lecture on stream processing and planned to use the Twitter streaming API as an example. To provide a framework for the attendees, I created the one below. It has been tested with Python 3.4 but as it does not include testing or other things it should only be used as an example.
from threading import Thread from collections import deque from twython import TwythonStreamer from requests.</description></item><item><title>Notes on The Anatomy of Courage</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-the-anatomy-of-courage.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-the-anatomy-of-courage.html</guid><description>Just a quick summary as I don&amp;rsquo;t really have detailed notes for this book.
The Anatomy of Courage is a quick read, and is interspersed with anecdotal accounts from Moran&amp;rsquo;s time as a doctor in the trenches in World War 1. The interesting part about books such as this is the applicability of the ideas contained therein to the workplace. The book says &amp;ldquo;Courage is will-power, whereof no man has an unlimited stock&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; In other words, for this book courage can be considered the will to continue an action in the face of danger or other difficulties.</description></item><item><title>Notes on John Maxwell's Five Levels of Leadership</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-john-maxwells-five-levels-of-leadership.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-john-maxwells-five-levels-of-leadership.html</guid><description>Leadership is influence.
Note: when you talk about your vision with people, they see you through the lens of these levels. So the person who sees you in level 1 will not absorb or be motivated by the vision in the same way as someone who sees you in level 4.
Level 1: Rights You get the position and the title. Basically nothing here besides imparted authority. People follow you because it&amp;rsquo;s their job, or they must for some reason.</description></item><item><title>Notes on Learning to Eat Soup with a Knife</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-learning-to-eat-soup-with-a-knife.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-learning-to-eat-soup-with-a-knife.html</guid><description>Chapter 1 What is a &amp;ldquo;Learning Organization?&amp;rdquo;
Does it promote suggestions from lower ranks and from operational areas (i.e. people &amp;ldquo;on the ground&amp;rdquo;)?
Are subordinates encouraged to question superiors and policies?
Does the organization regularly question its basic assumptions?
Are executives and other management routinely in close contact with operational people and open to their suggestions?
The three key elements to The Learning Challenge of Sullivan and Harper from the book Hope is Not a Method:</description></item><item><title>Notes on The Mission, the Men, and Me</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-the-mission-the-men-and-me.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/notes-on-the-mission-the-men-and-me.html</guid><description>Part 1 Don&amp;rsquo;t get treed by a Chiuahua. That is, don&amp;rsquo;t make snap decisions before you have collected and processed a sufficient amount of information to decide. When it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to decide, develop the situation.
Humor your imagination.
Part 2 The mind goes through 3 phases during learning and planning. Saturate, incubate, illuminate. They occur more or less in order, but your mind continuously cycles through each phase. Incubation-induced sleep loss is common though sleep is needed in order to maintain optimal chances of illumination (page 70).</description></item><item><title>CSAP - Collect, Store, Analyze, Productize</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/csap-collect-store-analyze-productize.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/csap-collect-store-analyze-productize.html</guid><description>Introduction Compared with many disciplines and areas, Data Science is extremely new and the scope of a Data Science team inside an organization is still a matter of debate. Since Data Science is an amalgamation of many different areas and specialties, including mathematics, computer science, statistics, machine learning, business, economics, and others, there so far hasn&amp;rsquo;t been many clear frameworks or organizational structures to support a Data Science group. Regardless of the implementation details, a company looking to improve its overall standing from a data perspective will want a specialist group who focuses on how data is collected, stored, analyzed, and productized (CSAP).</description></item><item><title>Data Science and Organizational Structure</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/data-science-and-organizational-structure.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/data-science-and-organizational-structure.html</guid><description>Introduction When a company wants to make data one of the prime focuses of the business, often the first problem that arises is how to fit a Data Science team into the current organizational structure. Similar problems have risen in the past with Business Intelligence/Business Analytics, and other disciplines, but the reason that Data Science presents a different problem is because it is a superset of previous areas in terms of technical and business scope.</description></item><item><title>Command-line Tools can be 235x Faster than your Hadoop Cluster</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/command-line-tools-can-be-235x-faster-than-your-hadoop-cluster.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/command-line-tools-can-be-235x-faster-than-your-hadoop-cluster.html</guid><description>Introduction As I was browsing the web and catching up on some sites I visit periodically, I found a cool article from Tom Hayden about using Amazon Elastic Map Reduce (EMR) and mrjob in order to compute some statistics on win/loss ratios for chess games he downloaded from the millionbase archive, and generally have fun with EMR. Since the data volume was only about 1.75GB containing around 2 million chess games, I was skeptical of using Hadoop for the task, but I can understand his goal of learning and having fun with mrjob and EMR.</description></item><item><title>Real-Time Bidding, First and Second-Price Auctions, and Transparency</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/real-time-bidding-first-and-second-price-auctions-and-transparency.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/real-time-bidding-first-and-second-price-auctions-and-transparency.html</guid><description>There has been some debate recently on AdExchanger about the benefits of first price versus second price auctions. Esco Strong, the Director of Display Marketplace Strategy for Microsoft Advertising wrote an article that basically said second price auctions didn&amp;rsquo;t work well for single unit RTB auctions and we should get rid of them:
Comparatively, first-price auctions are competitions where there is no reduction in clearing price for the auction winner; instead, the winner simply acquires the good they have won by paying the price of their bid.</description></item><item><title>MAC Addresses, UDIDs, and Privacy</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/mac-addresses-udids-and-privacy.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/mac-addresses-udids-and-privacy.html</guid><description>There has been quite a bit of fuss in the days since Apple started rejecting apps that make use of the UDID. The deprecation was announced months ago, but the rejection started without warning and was a surprise to some. Firms that had been planning for the change typically already had multiple secondary solutions in place, many of which rely on using the Media Access Control (MAC) address from the wireless network interface controller (wireless NIC) on the device.</description></item><item><title>UDID is Gone. So What?</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/udid-is-gone.-so-what.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/udid-is-gone.-so-what.html</guid><description>The last week has seen quite a bit of commotion in the mobile world as Apple has started enforcing their long-awaited deprecation of the use of the UDID. Honestly, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what all the fuss is about. This change was announced by Apple last summer, so everyone has had nearly a year to prepare for it. The general set of questions I&amp;rsquo;ve seen on the topic can be reduced to the following.</description></item><item><title>On Big Data and Spurious Correlations</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-big-data-and-spurious-correlations.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-big-data-and-spurious-correlations.html</guid><description>I didn&amp;rsquo;t have time to mention it last week, but even though I am happy that the New York Times wrote an article on big data, I think the most interesting part was at the end:
Big Data has its perils, to be sure. With huge data sets and fine-grained measurement, statisticians and computer scientists note, there is increased risk of false discoveries. The trouble with seeking a meaningful needle in massive haystacks of data, says Trevor Hastie, a statistics professor at Stanford, is that many bits of straw look like needles.</description></item><item><title>What Mobile Advertising Needs</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/what-mobile-advertising-needs.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/what-mobile-advertising-needs.html</guid><description>The advertising world is both feeding, and being fed a lot of hype about the current state and potential of mobile advertising. It&amp;rsquo;s no doubt that this form of marketing is unique in many ways, and offers opportunities not available via other forms of advertising. As an example, on mobile you can take advantage of information like a relatively precise knowledge of the location of the individual. Now, it is debatable whether such granular knowledge of a person&amp;rsquo;s location is a good, bad, or neutral thing, but the fact remains that this piece of information is something that simply has not been available to advertisers until recently.</description></item><item><title>Don't Ship What Doesn't Work</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/dont-ship-what-doesnt-work.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/dont-ship-what-doesnt-work.html</guid><description>If involved in workflow engineering, technology-related or otherwise, do everyone a favor and don&amp;rsquo;t pass something to the next stage if the previous stage isn&amp;rsquo;t done properly. Shigeru Miyamoto, the creator of Mario and the Legend of Zelda knows this. Take his words to heart:
A late game is only late until it ships. A bad game is bad until the end of time. &amp;ndash;Shigeru Miyamoto
If you pass a project on to the next stage of the workflow when it isn&amp;rsquo;t perfect, eventually it will have to regress back and be repaired.</description></item><item><title>The Dismal Jobs Report, Economic Recovery, and Normalcy Bias</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/the-dismal-jobs-report-economic-recovery-and-normalcy-bias.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/the-dismal-jobs-report-economic-recovery-and-normalcy-bias.html</guid><description>Well everyone is reacting with shock and amazement at the negative June jobs report, which showed that contrary to the 125,000 jobs that even the most pessimistic economists expected to be added to the economy, the actual number was in fact about 18,000. This isn&amp;rsquo;t surprising, as this recovery will take a long time. In fact, it will take longer than most people expect and that is due in part to something called Normalcy Bias.</description></item><item><title>Uncorrelated Does NOT Imply Independent</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/uncorrelated-does-not-imply-independent.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/uncorrelated-does-not-imply-independent.html</guid><description>This is just an aside to describe a misconception that we have seen some money managers make when describing their strategies or portfolios. When you are discussing the correlation of your portfolio to another portfolio or the market in general, the fact that your portfolio may be fairly uncorrelated does not have anything to do with the independence of your portfolio from a reference portfolio or the market in general. In fact, even if the portfolio you have developed is completely uncorrelated, it still probably isn&amp;rsquo;t independent.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on the Efficient Market Hypothesis</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/thoughts-on-the-efficient-market-hypothesis.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/thoughts-on-the-efficient-market-hypothesis.html</guid><description>The Efficient Market Hypothesis (EMH) is both important and often misunderstood. For our purposes, the term efficient is related to informational efficiency, or how quickly information affects prices. In a way, the level of informational efficiency in a market tells you what level of randomness to expect and consequently if it is possible to outperform the market. In its simplest form, the EMH states that market prices reflect decisions made by participants who have acted rationally based on information they possess.</description></item><item><title>Market Commentary, Correlation, and Causation</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/market-commentary-correlation-and-causation.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/market-commentary-correlation-and-causation.html</guid><description>Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled, this isn&amp;rsquo;t market commentary. This is commentary about market commentary. Many times when we come across market commentary, we see horrible examples of confusing correlation and causation, the logical fallacy of post hoc ergo propter hoc wherein event B is said to be caused by event A simply because event B followed A. This fallacy can be found in the vast majority of market commentary, and is especially obvious on days where the market didn&amp;rsquo;t move appreciably, yet there is someone claiming to know why the move occurred.</description></item><item><title>On Technical Analysis, Fractals, and Stock Prices</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/on-technical-analysis-fractals-and-stock-prices.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/on-technical-analysis-fractals-and-stock-prices.html</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking recently about fractal geometry with applications to finance, and I talked to an acquaintance who informed me that he watches the &amp;ldquo;fractals&amp;rdquo; on his charts when trading. This prompted me to do some research into how technical analysts use &amp;ldquo;fractals&amp;rdquo; and see what kind of information such an indicator provides. There are many issues with using fractal behavior as a technical indicator, namely that the way the term is used in technical analysis doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like it has anything to do with fractals at all.</description></item><item><title>Computing Ornstein-Uhlenbeck Process Trajectories in R</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/computing-ornstein-uhlenbeck-process-trajectories-in-r.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/computing-ornstein-uhlenbeck-process-trajectories-in-r.html</guid><description>Compared to the Ruby version, computing this in R is much easier due to the built-in stochastic differential equation simulator. Assuming you have R installed, make sure you also install the sde package. Here is all the initial work that cleans up everything from your workspace, sets the initial value of the process, the end-point, how granular you want the simulation to be, and how many trajectories you want.
rm(list = ls(all = TRUE)) x0 = 50 end_point = 200 discretization_factor = 100 total_steps = end_point * discretization_factor #Use the same seed for multiple trajectories if (number_trajectories &amp;gt; 1) number_trajectories = 1 set.</description></item><item><title>Computing Ornstein-Uhlenbeck Process Trajectories in Ruby</title><link>https://adamdrake.com/computing-ornstein-uhlenbeck-process-trajectories-in-ruby.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adamdrake.com/computing-ornstein-uhlenbeck-process-trajectories-in-ruby.html</guid><description>This code is adapted from some Matlab code I found that simulates the OU process exactly. I had to code up a quick Gaussian random number generator in Ruby because I didn&amp;rsquo;t find a method to handle that. As noted in the comments I used the Box-Muller Transformation but if lots of random numbers are required the Ziggurat Algorithm could be used instead.
#!/usr/bin/env ruby include Math require &amp;#39;rubygems&amp;#39; require &amp;#39;gnuplot&amp;#39; #Gaussian random number generator using the Box-Muller Transformation #If this is too slow it can be replaced with the Ziggurat Algorithm def randn z1 = rand z2 = rand rand_normal = sqrt(-2.</description></item></channel></rss>